Finding aid to Alumnae Oral History Project collection CA.MS.00301
Smith College Archives
- Alumnae Oral History Project interviews (2014), Accession 2012-A-0026
  - Molly McNulty (Class of 1984) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Molly McNulty describes her time at Smith, beginning with her excitement about attending a women's college. McNulty speaks to the experience of arriving and feeling academically overwhelmed, dealing with depression after arrival, and the strong house community that helped her through a challenging time. She describes her social life and issues on campus that prompted student organizing around race and sexual orientation. McNulty speaks to the Smith party scene and the low drinking age, which had a profound effect on issues of sexual violence on campus. She discusses Smith as a feminist school during the 1980s and the desire for students to shape their own experience. She also speaks to the presence of lesbian organizations on campus, sexual experimentation, and a general environment of excitement.
    - Video interview with Molly McNulty
    - Transcript of interview with Molly McNulty (Box 12)
  - Susan O'Malley (Class of 1964) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Susan O'Malley begins with a small note of being placed in the maid's quarters in King House. During this segment, O'Malley refers to a Kingsman (groundskeeper) who mentions that there were a number of suicides at Smith committed in the quad. O'Malley then discusses her dating life, the rigid curfew, and Father's Weekend as issues that were shaped by the restrictive culture of Smith. O'Malley also mentions her amusing stint playing the carillon. She speaks of visiting sex lecturers at Smith, her post-grad experiences in the South, the Smith posture pictures as an invasive practice, and the overall homophobic culture of Smith in the 1960s.
    - Video interview with Susan O'Malley
    - Transcript of interview with Susan O'Malley (Box 12)
  - Katherine Panfil (Class of 1964) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Kathie Panfil begins her interview by recalling her time living in Albright and some of the house traditions in which she participated. She talks about the challenges of coming from a less prestigious high school than other Smithies. She discusses the student reactions to George Wallace coming to speak, as well as the overall revision of her political views that she went through while at Smith. Next, she remembers the assassination of JFK. She discusses her experience of the rules and regulations that the college placed on social life. Moving on to academics, Panfil brings up the importance of having enough focus in one's major and the influence of Dean Robinton. Finally, she recalls the expectation that she would get married right after college rather than start a career, and the extent to which she did and did not fulfill this expectation.
    - Video interview with Katherine Panfil
    - Transcript of interview with Katherine Panfil (Box 12)
  - Caroline Pinto (Class of 2004) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Caro Pinto begins the interview by remembering positive interactions with Smith alumnae that led her to apply. She discusses the queer community at Smith, the "politically correct" culture, and the political climate of the college. Pinto speaks positively about controversies at Smith and reflects on how the conversations that came out of controversies were helpful for many. She also chronicles her time at Smith in relationship to major national events such as the Bush v. Gore election and 9/11. Pinto ends the interview by discussing her career path in archival work after Smith.
    - Video interview with Caroline Pinto
    - Transcript of interview with Caroline Pinto (Box 12)
  - Yolanda Rael (Class of 1994) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Rael discusses her experience coming to Smith from a lower-middle-class Latino family. She describes herself as a feminist from a young age who decided to prioritize her education. Rael describes the experience of living in Cutter House, which was experiencing intense racial tensions within the house community. She recalls the story of watching Salt N' Peppa come to Smith and the opening act being Woody Heralson, who made a racially charged comment on the Rodney King trial. Rael describes feeling depressed and stressed in Cutter House, and eventually moving to Lawrence House for a calmer environment. Towards the end of the interview, Rael continues to come back to the idea of Smith as a hardworking and nurturing environment. Her comments frequently return to nurturing her student-self through challenging times by going on walks and working hard.
    - Video interview with Yolanda Rael
    - Transcript of interview with Yolanda Rael (Box 12)
  - Elizabeth Risberg (Class of 1984) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Elizabeth Risberg recalls both social and academic life at Smith, as well as her experience as a Head Resident. She talks about the political culture on campus, the Jeane Kirkpatrick commencement speaker controversy, and the Reagan election. Elizabeth recalls the weekly dance parties at Smith that were a source of stress relief for many students. She talks about her career change from journalism to public relations after graduating from Smith, and ends the interview by advising current Smith students to explore their options and go abroad if possible.
    - Video interview with Elizabeth Risberg
    - Transcript of interview with Elizabeth Risberg (Box 12)
  - Lisa Sankowski (Class of 1984) and Emily Newburger (Class of 1984) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Emily Newburger and Lisa Sankowski begin their interview with the story of how they met in Park House, became friends, and eventually became romantically involved. They discuss the attitudes towards lesbianism on campus as well as the separatist culture present in Hover and Tenney Houses and the closing of Hover. Later, they talk about getting married, issues of gender identity on campus, and the normalizing of lesbianism in more recent years. Sankowski recalls her experiences being Head Resident of Jordan House, and both women talk about the parallels between the controversies over Jeane Kirkpatrick and Christine Lagarde being chosen as commencement speakers. Additionally, they remember favorite traditions from their time at Smith and describe their careers since graduation.
    - Video interview with Emily Newburger and Lisa Sankowski
    - Transcript of interview with Emily Newburger and Lisa Sankowski (Box 12)
  - Agnes Bundy Scanlan (Class of 1979) interviewed by Nina Goldman, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, current trustee Agnes Scanlan discusses how Smith being a women's college affected her decision to attend. Scanlan describes the political atmosphere of the late '70s as an extension of the early '70s, with many different student groups on campus advocating for rights and visibility. She talks about growing up in a variety of different places and social cultures and how this prepared her for the multi-cultural environment of Smith. Scanlan also speaks to the perks of attending a women's college, the five-college social scene, and balancing her social life with her academic work. She closes with advice to current Smith students and reflection on her Smith experience.
    - Video interview with Agnes Bundy Scanian
    - Transcript of interview with Agnes Bundy Scanian (Box 12)
  - Gail Stempien (Class of 1964) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Gail Stempien talks about some of her favorite house and college traditions. She recalls the strictness of her house mother, the weekend curfews, and dating culture at Smith. She remembers meeting Ted Kennedy with one of her classes, and her professor's reaction to him. Stempien concludes the interview by discussing her time at Smith as a moment of opportunity and privilege.
    - Video interview with Gail Stempien
    - Transcript of interview with Gail Stempien (Box 12)
  - Carol Sudhalter (Class of 1964) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Carol Sudhalter talks about feeling removed from many of her classmates when she was at Smith and discusses her frequent ventures off-campus into the surrounding area. She recalls the class and racial tensions that led her house mother to forbid her friendship with a black cook. Finally, she talks about her love for and career in music and how it led her back to Smith for reunion.
    - Video interview with Carol Sudhalter
    - Transcript of interview with Carol Sudhalter (Box 12)
  - Jane Thurber (Class of 1964) interviewed by Grace Ramsay, 2014 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Jane Thurber begins her interview with the story of coming to Smith as a result of the music program and her sister's attendance before her. She talks about feeling younger than her other friends in Wilder House. She moves on to discuss her music major and her career in teaching music, and closes by speaking to the importance of listening to other people's opinions and being grateful for the opportunities that Smith affords.
    - Video interview with Jane Thurber
    - Transcript of interview with Jane Thurber (Box 12)
  - Rachel Willis (Class of 2004) interviewed by Julia Greider, 2014 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Rachel Willis begins her interview with the story of coming to Smith as a result of her sister attending before her. She recalls the campus reaction to 9/11. She moves on to tell about her close relationships with her friends in Wilder House and some of the pranks that they organized. She next talks about being on the croquet team all four years. Willis discusses the difficulties involved in the change of presidents from Ruth Simmons to Carol Christ, as well as the sense of pressure she felt to do great things after graduation. She recalls what it was like to be African American on campus and the reactions to racist incidents in the Quad. Willis concludes by talking about the role of the Internet in her college experience and the value of her relationships with professors.
    - Video interview with Rachel Willis
    - Transcript of interview with Rachel Willis (Box 12)
- Alumnae Oral History Project interviews (2015), Accession 2016-A-0001
  - Lisa Abrams (Class of 1990) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 22; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Lisa Abrams discusses her introduction to Smith via a Mt. Holyoke graduate, her tight knit house community and the lasting relationships that resulted. Abrams also talks about her study abroad experience and how it impacted her return to campus, as well as her work study experience in the dean's office. She details her post Smith educational career and how invaluable her Smith education was in helping her to achieve her goals.
    - Video interview with Lisa Abrams
    - Transcript of interview with Lisa Abrams (Box 13)
  - Pamela Jean (Riley) Akiri (Class of 1965) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Pamela Jeanne Akiri discusses her academic life at Smith, pursuing a zoology major and how her Smith career influenced her post-grad career choices. She details her first marriage, the difficulties she and her husband faced as an interracial couple in the U.S. in the late 1960s and their subsequent move to Nigeria for work.
    - Video interview with Pamela Jean Akiri
    - Transcript of interview with Pamela Jean Akiri (Box 13)
  - Lauren Barth-Cohen (Class of 2005) interviewed by Hana Sarfan, 2015 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Lauren Barth-Cohen discusses her Smith experience, academic challenges and triumphs. She recalls her positive experience as a physics major and credits notable professors in the science department. Barth-Cohen details her post Smith career trajectory in the male dominated physics field and how her difficulties steered her toward teaching and engineering.
    - Video interview with Lauren Barth-Cohen
    - Transcript of interview with Lauren Barth-Cohen (Box 13)
  - Carol Berde (Class of 1965) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Carol Berde discusses her apprehension upon arriving at Smith, how she eventually found her footing, despite religious segregation, in part by becoming president of Wilder house and her involvement with the honor board. She recounts the political culture at Smith during the Civil Rights Movement, regret at not being more involved out of fear, and her memory of the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. Berde details her life and career after Smith, particularly her work with Planned Parenthood of Minnesota, and offers unique personal insights regarding the evolution of student engagement pertaining to political and social justice issues on and off campus.
    - Video interview with Carol Berde
    - Transcript of interview with Carol Berde (Box 13)
  - Abby Berns (Class of 2008) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 23; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Abby Berns begins her interview discussing the factors that led her to choose Smith. She recounts her experiences within the Jewish community and the climate on campus during the Bush administration. She discusses the contention surrounding Christine Legarde's rescinded commencement speech and relates it to a similar incident during her undergraduate years. Berns details the advantages of having attended a women's college and the benefits it has afforded her after Smith and in the field of public health.
    - Video interview with Abby Berns
    - Transcript of interview with Abby Berns (Box 13)
  - Katherine "Kathy" Boulton (AC 1990) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 23; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Kathy Boulton discusses her introduction to Smith College, the Ada Comstock Scholars program and subsequent admission. She talks about her experience as a non-traditional student in and out of the classroom and details specific incidences where age a life experience benefited and hindered her experience within the Smith community. She credits Jill Ker Conway and Eli Rothman with providing women an opportunity to continue their education and stresses how important her Smith education has been in furthering her career, increasing her earning capacity and ability to think both critically and analytically.
    - Video interview with Katherine Boulton
    - Transcript of interview with Katherine Boulton (Box 13)
  - Adelaide Cromwell (Class of 1940) interviewed by Hana Sarfan, 2015 May 23; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Adelaide Cromwell recounts the influence her aunt, Otelia Cromwell, had on her decision to attend Smith, and her acceptance into the Smith community as one of four admitted African American students at the college. She discusses social and academic life on campus at the time and the lasting friendships that developed. Cromwell recounts her interest in sociology and how her education at Smith benefited her post-Smith career. She discusses career milestones; establishing an African American studies program at Boston University being the first African American woman to teach at Hunter College and later at Smith. Cromwell offers her insight as to how to college has evolved, socially and politically, citing the admission of transwomen as proof of progress.
    Cromwell, Adelaide M., Class of 1940
    - Video interview with Adelaide Cromwell
    - Transcript of interview with Adelaide Cromwell (Box 13)
  - Jennifer "Jenny" Dandy (Class of 1980) interviewed by Tanya Pearsonn, 2015 May 22; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Jenny Dandy recollects her move from California to Massachusetts and her transition into the Smith community. She discusses the 'typical Smithie' style, academic areas of interest, memorable professors and poignant classroom experiences. Dandy also the political climate on campus in the late 1970s with the arrival of the Women's Studies Program and Lesbian Alliance student organization that vocalized LGBT issues.
    - Video interview with Jennifer "Jenny" Dandy
    - Transcript of interview with Jennifer "Jenny" Dandy (Box 13)
  - Mary Jo Deering (Class of 1965) interviewed by Hana Sarfan, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Mary Jo Deering discusses her transition from public high school and the inspiration she derived from Smith's academic community. She recalls her junior year abroad in France and her introduction to oral history as a result of that trip. Deering also recounts the first African American Studies courses offered at Smith and the resulting contestation. She credits her Smith education in fostering a set of critical thinking skills that remain with her today.
    - Video interview with Mary Jo Deering
    - Transcript of interview with Mary Jo Deering (Box 13)
  - Paula Ferris Einaudi (Class of 1965) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 15-16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Paula Ferris Einaudi discusses her desire to attend Smith from an early age and the limited choices available to women at that time. She reflects on her feelings upon arrival as a freshman and the personal transformation that occurred during those four years. Einaudi details her house community, social and dating life on and off campus, the political climate during the Women's Movement and Civil Rights Movement, as well as gender, sexuality and the evolution of Smith's student body. Einudi expands upon her post Smith life and career, specifically how Smith remains an influential presence via networking and alumnae.
    - Video interview with Paula Ferris Einaudi
    - Transcript of interview with Paula Ferris Einaudi (Box 13)
  - Shamiram Feinglass (Class of 1990) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 22; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Shamiram Feinglass discusses her arrival at Smith, house community and rich social life. She describes an atmosphere of inclusivity and diversity but also details a number of racist incidences on campus in the late 1980s. Feinglass comments on the typical Smithie, details her post Smith career and stresses the importance of leveraging the Smith network.
    - Video interview with Shamiram Feinglass
    - Transcript of interview with Shamiram Feinglass (Box 13)
  - Yvonne Garrett (Class of 1985) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 17; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Yvonne Garrett discusses the difficult acclimation to Smith and the fashion and culture that was popular on campus at the time. Garrett describes her experience as an outsider, a goth, and how the campus and student body has evolved since the 1980s. Garrett reflects on her post Smith career and what it's like to return to campus and participate in the Smith traditions that she opposed as an undergrad.
    - Video interview with Yvonne Garrett
    - Transcript of interview with Yvonne Garrett (Box 13)
  - Dr. Evelyn Boyd Granville (Class of 1945) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 22; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Dr. Evelyn Boyd Granville begins her interview recounting her time at Dunbar High School in Washington, D.C., and the educators who encouraged the student body to apply to 'Ivy League' colleges. She describes her personal experience as the only African American student in her graduating class, campus life during WWII, academic interests, achievements, memorable internship opportunities, and favorite Smith traditions. Granville describes her post-Smith academic career, becoming the second woman to earn a Ph.D. in mathematics in 1949, and her career trajectory from joining IBM in 1956, to working NASA's Project Vanguard and Project Mercury space programs. She details her career in education and life after retirement.
    Granville, Evelyn Boyd, Class of 1945, Dr.
    - Video interview with Dr. Evelyn Boyd Granville
    - Transcript of interview with Dr. Evelyn Boyd Granville (Box 13)
  - Francine Haber (Class of 1965) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Francine Haber recounts her arrival at Smith in 1961 and its reputation as the "Ivy League" college for women. She describes her house community, strict rules and regulations, the roles of house mothers and social life on and off campus. She describes the atmosphere on campus at the start of Vietnam War, her participation in the Civil Rights Student movement (SNCC), and the contention surrounding George Wallace's invitation to speak at Smith. Haber details her junior year abroad in London and credits her Smith education with shaping her formative years in a way that benefited her personally and professionally.
    - Video interview with Francine Haber
    - Transcript of interview with Francine Haber (Box 13)
  - Jona Burgess Hammer (Class of 1965) interviewed by Hana Sarfan, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Jona Burgess Hammer describes moving from Iceland to the United States and the cultural differences she encountered as a student at Smith, particularly her surprise at discovering Smith was a single sex institution. She details social life on campus in the early 1960s, specifically mixers and dances in which men from neighboring colleges were brought to Smith, and how she met her husband at the first mixer she begrudgingly attended. She her English major, coursework and notable professors and the overall conservative climate of the Smith campus in the early 1960s.
    - Video interview with Jona Burgess Hammer
    - Transcript of interview with Jona Burgess Hammer (Box 13)
  - Christine Heyworth (Class of 1965) interviewed by Izzy Levy, 2015 May 16; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Chrissy Heyworth describes her transition from a small farmhouse in eastern Massachusetts to communal living in the modern Ziskind dorm. She recalls the close, lifelong friendship she and her roommate developed, and details the diversity that was particular to the Cutter Ziskind community. Heyworth describes social life and dating as well as the challenge in balancing her athletics and studies. She discusses the evolution of the Smith student population and offers her perspective on issues of sexuality, gender and identity.
    - Video interview with Christine Heyworth
    - Transcript of interview with Christine Heyworth (Box 13)
  - Collyn Hinchey (Class of 2005) interviewed by Tanya Pearson, 2015 May 15; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this interview, Collyn Hinchey discusses how she chose Smith College and the ensuing transition away from home and family and assimilation into campus life. She talks about her involvement with the campus radio station, her job at the Sophia Smith Collection and relationships with friends and professors. Hinchey also recounts the climate on campus following the attacks on September 11th, 2001, and contention surrounding the reelection of George W. Bush. She also describes her affinity for certain Smith traditions that remain in the midst of change.
    - Video interview with Collyn Hinchey
    - Transcript of interview with Collyn Hinchey (Box 13)